<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short discourse of the true knowledge of Christ Jesus to which are added some passages in the reasonableness of Christianity &amp;c. and its vindication : with some animadversions on Mr. Edward's reflections on the reasonableness of Christianity and on his book entituled Socinianism unmask'd / by S. Bold.</title>
            <author>Bold, S. (Samuel), 1649-1737.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24663</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08402838</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08402838</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41276</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28599)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41276)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1247:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short discourse of the true knowledge of Christ Jesus to which are added some passages in the reasonableness of Christianity &amp;c. and its vindication : with some animadversions on Mr. Edward's reflections on the reasonableness of Christianity and on his book entituled Socinianism unmask'd / by S. Bold.</title>
                  <author>Bold, S. (Samuel), 1649-1737.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. and J. Churchil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Knowableness.</term>
               <term>Edwards, John, 1637-1716. --  Socinianism unmask'd.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41276:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41276:1"/>
            <p>A SHORT DISCOURSE OF THE True Knowledge OF <hi>CHRIST JESUS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which are Added, Some Paſſages in the <hi>Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of Chriſtianity,</hi> &amp;c. and its <hi>Vindication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With ſome <hi>Animadverſions</hi> on Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>'s <hi>Reflections</hi> on the <hi>Reaſonableneſs of Chriſtianity,</hi> and on his Book, Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>Socinianiſm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmask'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>S. Bold,</hi> Rector of <hi>Steeple, Dorſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>For other Foundation can no Man lay than that is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt, <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 3.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>J. Churchil</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Row.</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41276:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41276:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Philip. III. 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Yea doubtleſs, and I count all things but loſs for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Apoſtle doth not here ſpeak of any thing that was <hi>proper</hi> to himſelf either as an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> or a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of an <hi>extraordinary growth,</hi> but what was <hi>common</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> with every <hi>True Believer,</hi> or ſincere <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> For theſe words are but part of the <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> he annexes of that <hi>Property</hi> of true Believers of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> he had laid down in the laſt Clauſe of the third Verſe of this Chapter, who <hi>have no confidence in the Fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſeventh Verſe he relates the different <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> he had of Matters with relation to <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:41276:3"/> and <hi>Salvation</hi> before he was <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted,</hi> from what he had of them after his <hi>Converſion.</hi> Thoſe things which before his <hi>Converſion</hi> he reckon'd <hi>Gain, i. e.</hi> which he thought were the <hi>matter</hi> of a Perſons <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> the things which being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd would <hi>Juſtifie,</hi> and render a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>acceptable</hi> to God, and <hi>warrant</hi> his being <hi>confident</hi> of <hi>Salvation,</hi> he accounted <hi>Loſs,</hi> after he was effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Regenerated:</hi> Becauſe he then knew that <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone is our <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> and that he only can <hi>ſave</hi> us.</p>
            <p>In theſe words he declares again, with great <hi>Earneſtneſs,</hi> that he looks upon the poſſeſſion and enjoyment of all thoſe things he formerly thought would <hi>conſtitute</hi> Perſons <hi>Righteous</hi> and Happy, and every thing elſe <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct</hi> from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that any can place their confidence in, to be of no more <hi>moment</hi> and conſideration to theſe <hi>Purpoſes</hi> than heaps of <hi>Dung,</hi> and <hi>Droſs</hi> can be to the <hi>nouriſhing</hi> of a Man's <hi>natural Life,</hi> and to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of him <hi>Wealthy.</hi> And as <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne is our Righteouſneſs, and he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41276:3"/> only can <hi>juſtifie</hi> and <hi>ſave</hi> us, ſo it is by the <hi>knowledge of Chriſt,</hi> that we come to be <hi>intereſted</hi> in <hi>Him,</hi> and to receive from him <hi>thoſe,</hi> and all thoſe ſingular and ineſtimable <hi>Benefits</hi> and <hi>Bleſſings</hi> He is <hi>intruſted</hi> to <hi>diſpence.</hi> This knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus is ſo <hi>adapted</hi> to this <hi>end,</hi> hath ſuch a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion</hi> with it, by Divine <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Appointment,</hi> hath ſuch an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency</hi> in it, ſuch a <hi>Power, Efficacy,</hi> and <hi>Virtue</hi> for the deriving of theſe Mercies and Bleſſings to us from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that all other things are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly <hi>inſignificant</hi> to this purpoſe, but when <hi>depended</hi> on for <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> are a very great <hi>Detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Damage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order to a more diſtinct under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of theſe words, I will briefly conſider four things in them, and then conclude with ſhewing ſome <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> we ſhould make of what ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed.</p>
            <p>The Four things I ſhall briefly conſider are, Firſt, <hi>The matter of this Knowledge the Apoſtle ſpeaks of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>What kind of Knowledge it is of this point, which the Apoſtle
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41276:4"/> doth thus</hi> magnifie <hi>and</hi> extol, <hi>and give ſuch a preference to?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Wherein the</hi> excellency <hi>of this Knowledge doth conſiſt?</hi> And,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>The account the Perſon who knows Chriſt Jeſus</hi> aright, <hi>doth make of all other things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall conſider what is the <hi>matter</hi> of this Knowledge the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of, or what is the <hi>object</hi> to be known. This he expreſſeth in theſe words, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> that is, that the <hi>Perſon,</hi> God had promiſed to <hi>ſend</hi> into the World to be the <hi>Saviour of Sinners,</hi> was <hi>Him</hi> who is <hi>generally known,</hi> and was <hi>ſignally diſtinguiſhed</hi> from other People by this Name <hi>Jeſus;</hi> or that He who is commonly known, and peculiarly ſpoken of by this name <hi>Jeſus,</hi> is the Perſon God did deſign, and promiſe to ſend into the World to be the Saviour of Sinners. That this <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Perſon God hath <hi>anointed</hi> and <hi>commiſſioned</hi> to this <hi>Office;</hi> and that He is the <hi>only</hi> and the <hi>all-ſufficient,</hi> and moſt <hi>gracious Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> of <hi>Sinners.</hi> That <hi>Jeſus is the Chriſt</hi> (the Perſon God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned to be the Saviour of Sinners)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41276:4"/> is the <hi>Propoſition</hi> I conceive the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle here ſpeaks of, the object of that Knowledge here commended. And this is the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſtrictly and moſt properly conſidered, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12. The fulfilling of the <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> which went before concerning the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> or the Perſon God had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to <hi>ſend,</hi> in this <hi>Jeſus;</hi> and his declaring that he was that <hi>Perſon,</hi> and doing <hi>ſuch things</hi> to confirm the truth of what he <hi>Taught,</hi> as could not be <hi>wrought</hi> and effected but by the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi> and <hi>immediate Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> afford ſufficient <hi>Evidence</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Men of the truth of this <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> that <hi>Jeſus is the Chriſt.</hi> This I take to be the matter or object of that Knowledge the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of. Not that I think a bare <hi>ſpeculative Knowledge</hi> of this <hi>Article</hi> or <hi>Propoſition</hi> is the <hi>Knowledge</hi> the Apoſtle doth thus <hi>magnifie</hi> and ſet ſuch a <hi>value on.</hi> Therefore I ſhall conſider,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> What <hi>kind of Knowledge of this Propoſition it is, the Apoſtle doth here ſpeak of.</hi> And it is ſuch a Knowledge as doth effectually deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41276:5"/> the Perſon, and cauſe him to <hi>reſign</hi> up himſelf <hi>entirely</hi> to <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> to be ſaved by him in his <hi>own way.</hi> Such a knowledge of him, as makes the Perſon to <hi>take</hi> him for <hi>his Lord;</hi> ſo that he will uſe his <hi>ſerious, honeſt,</hi> and <hi>beſt endeavours</hi> to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what he hath taught and reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and will <hi>aſſent</hi> to, <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</hi> whatever he ſhall attain to know He hath taught or revealed; and will <hi>depend</hi> wholly on <hi>Him</hi> to receive from <hi>Him</hi> in his <hi>own way,</hi> the <hi>benefits</hi> He is <hi>intruſted</hi> to <hi>diſpence.</hi> The no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and ſpeculative knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, hath its <hi>uſefulneſs,</hi> being the Foundation on which the other is builded, but it may be without the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and therefore is not <hi>ſaving,</hi> but the <hi>latter</hi> cannot be without the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> no more than a <hi>Superſtructure</hi> can be without a <hi>Foundation.</hi> A Man may have a notional knowledge of a Truth that is of extraordinary <hi>moment</hi> and <hi>uſefulneſs,</hi> and yet not be duly <hi>affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> with it; his knowledge may have little or no influence on him, becauſe he does not apply it to its proper <hi>end,</hi> he does not deſcend to conſider how
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41276:5"/> much it doth concern himſelf. Were there a Perſon that could infallibly cure ſome certain <hi>Diſtemper,</hi> and the proof of this Truth were moſt ſtrong and clear, ſo that there were no room for <hi>doubt</hi> and exception, a Perſon who does not apprehend himſelf annoyed with that <hi>Diſtemper,</hi> tho' he is ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that ſuch a Perſon can infallibly cure it, will not be prevailed with, and determined by his knowledge, to yield up himſelf abſolutely to his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,</hi> tho' when he comes to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that he is dangerouſly ill of that Diſeaſe, and that he cannot be cured any other way, but by committing himſelf entirely to that Perſon, his knowledge will have this effect on him, that he will <hi>render</hi> himſelf up entirely to his <hi>guidance</hi> and <hi>manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> When we are <hi>throughly ſenſible</hi> that we are <hi>Sinners,</hi> under the <hi>Curſe of the Law,</hi> and juſtly <hi>obnoxious</hi> to the moſt <hi>heavy diſpleaſure</hi> and <hi>wrath</hi> of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> and that there is no way for our obtaining <hi>Peace</hi> with <hi>Him, Pardon</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> but by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> then our knowing him to be the only, the all-ſufficient, and a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41276:6"/> moſt compaſſionate and gracious <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> of Sinners, will diſpoſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence us to <hi>reſign up our ſelves</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>reſervation</hi> to his <hi>Conduct,</hi> and to <hi>rely</hi> and <hi>depend</hi> on <hi>Him</hi> to ſave us in his <hi>own way.</hi> He <hi>came to ſeek and to ſave thoſe who are loſt,</hi> who are truly <hi>ſenſible</hi> of their <hi>loſt eſtate.</hi> All your <hi>knowledge</hi> will not avail you to <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> tho' you can <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> ever ſo <hi>accurately</hi> on every <hi>point</hi> in your <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> till it have this effect on you, to make you <hi>reſign</hi> up your ſelves <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly</hi> unto <hi>Christ</hi> as your <hi>Lord.</hi> But the Perſon who is brought to <hi>this,</hi> is <hi>Chriſt's Diſciple,</hi> a true <hi>Believer,</hi> and real <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> tho' as yet he does not know any other <hi>Doctrine</hi> Chriſt hath taught, but only engages <hi>hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to uſe his beſt endeavours to <hi>know</hi> and <hi>underſtand</hi> his <hi>Lord's Will,</hi> and to aſſent unto and perform the <hi>ſame,</hi> as he ſhall attain the <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>it;</hi> and reſolvedly applies himſelf to <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil</hi> and execute that <hi>engagement</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll <hi>Induſtry</hi> and <hi>Fidelity. This</hi> is that which <hi>conſtitutes</hi> and makes a Perſon a ſincere <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> a real <hi>Diſciple</hi> of Chriſt, and a true <hi>Believer.</hi> And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41276:6"/> his <hi>regular</hi> outward <hi>ſignifying</hi> and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying of this, gives him a <hi>Right</hi> to the external <hi>Denomination</hi> of a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> &amp;c. The true notional know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt Jeſus is the <hi>ſame</hi> for the <hi>matter,</hi> with the ſpiritual and practical knowledge of <hi>Him;</hi> but this latter makes the Perſon perceive the <hi>uſefulneſs</hi> and <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> to himſelf, and begets in him <hi>ſuitable Affections</hi> to Chriſt. He who thus knows <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is ſenſible, that He is the moſt neceſſary and uſeful <hi>Good</hi> to him, and therefore cannot but <hi>love</hi> him, <hi>reſign</hi> up himſelf <hi>entirely</hi> to Him, <hi>truſt</hi> in Him, and <hi>labour</hi> to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and know his <hi>Will,</hi> that he may <hi>explicitely</hi> believe what he hath <hi>taught,</hi> and <hi>actually</hi> obſerve and perform what he hath <hi>appointed</hi> and <hi>commanded,</hi> that thus he may <hi>approve</hi> his <hi>Fidelity,</hi> and <hi>obtain</hi> the <hi>ends</hi> particularly or more eſpecially intended by <hi>his Lord,</hi> in the ſeveral <hi>inſtances</hi> he ſhall <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> to be taught by <hi>Him,</hi> relating either to <hi>Belief</hi> or <hi>Practice.</hi> He knows that <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is <hi>worthy</hi> of all his <hi>Service,</hi> and therefore <hi>gives</hi> up himſelf unto Him, <hi>implicitly</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41276:7"/> without <hi>exception,</hi> to follow his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,</hi> both as to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi> Thus when he finds or underſtands, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath taught that He is <hi>God,</hi> and that He commiſſioned his Apoſtles to teach <hi>ſo,</hi> and that they did it very expreſly, he <hi>heartily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents</hi> to this <hi>Truth,</hi> and believes, that He is <hi>God,</hi> becauſe He hath taught it. And his not being able to ſolve all <hi>difficulties</hi> that <hi>curious</hi> and <hi>contentious People</hi> may ſtart about this <hi>matter;</hi> or to ſay much, or any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Mode,</hi> or way how He is God, is no <hi>obſtacle</hi> to his <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>ſtedfaſt Belief</hi> of <hi>it,</hi> ſeeing he knows Chriſt hath declared it; no more than his not being able to <hi>reconcile</hi> ſome <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>practice</hi> he underſtands Chriſt hath enjoyned him, to his <hi>worldly Intereſt,</hi> can excuſe him from performing it. Becauſe his <hi>Reſignation</hi> to Chriſt was abſolute and entire in both reſpects, and he did not <hi>Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> with Chriſt, to believe nothing but what he ſhould be able to <hi>dive</hi> to the <hi>bottom</hi> of, and give a <hi>rational ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> of the <hi>mode</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of, or to <hi>obey</hi> him only in ſuch <hi>Inſtances</hi> as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41276:7"/> he ſhould know how to reconcile to his <hi>worldly Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Convenience.</hi> What falls ſhort of this practical knowledge of <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> is not in Scripture account the <hi>knowledge of Christ Jeſus. He that ſaith I know him, and keepeth not his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is a lyar, and the truth is not in him,</hi> 1 John 2.4. This is that knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, the <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi> whereof is <hi>ſuch,</hi> it <hi>obſcures</hi> and <hi>ſtains</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of all things which can come in <hi>competition</hi> with <hi>it.</hi> So that the true Chriſtian accounts all things but <hi>loſs</hi> (as the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth himſelf) <hi>for the excellency of it.</hi> Which ſhall lead me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>In what the excellency of this knowledge of Christ Jeſus doth conſiſt.</hi> Concerning which I ſhall mention theſe particulars:</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. In the <hi>excellency of its object,</hi> (which is the revelation or diſcovery God hath made that Jeſus Chriſt is the Perſon He hath ſent and commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned to be the Saviour of Sinners) and in the <hi>proportion</hi> it hath to the <hi>ſpecial Intendment</hi> of that <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:41276:8"/> viz. that we may reſign up our ſelves intirely to him, and thereby be made his Diſciples, and be intereſted in Him, as our Saviour; or more briefly, that we may believe in Him, and be ſaved by him, or be made <hi>true Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>partake</hi> of the <hi>Benefits</hi> which belong to <hi>them.</hi> It is not the bare knowing that there was ſuch a <hi>Perſon</hi> as Jeſus Chriſt in the <hi>World,</hi> no nor that He was the <hi>Son of God,</hi> and <hi>aſſumed our Nature,</hi> &amp;c. but that He was <hi>ſent, appointed,</hi> and <hi>commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned</hi> by <hi>God</hi> to be the <hi>Saviour of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. This</hi> is the <hi>immediate,</hi> the moſt <hi>proper,</hi> and <hi>ſtrict object</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian knowledge,</hi> and ſaving Faith. Had the Son of God, meerly of his own <hi>accord,</hi> aſſumed our <hi>Nature,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the moſt <hi>perfect Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Law,</hi> and ſuffered <hi>Death</hi> for our ſakes, how great ſoever the <hi>intrinſick value</hi> of his <hi>Condeſcention, Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances,</hi> and <hi>Sufferings</hi> would have been, this would not have <hi>conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted</hi> or made Him the <hi>Saviour of Sinners:</hi> Nor would our <hi>knowing</hi> and <hi>believing</hi> all this, have <hi>availed</hi> us to <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Salvation.</hi> That
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41276:8"/> which makes what He <hi>did</hi> and <hi>ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> to be <hi>accepted</hi> for <hi>us,</hi> and <hi>makes</hi> Him the <hi>Saviour</hi> of <hi>Sinners,</hi> was his being <hi>appointed</hi> and <hi>commiſſioned</hi> to be their <hi>Saviour.</hi> And it is our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Him to be the Perſon that <hi>God</hi> did <hi>ſend</hi> and <hi>commiſſion</hi> for this <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> and <hi>knowing</hi> it <hi>ſo,</hi> as to anſwer the <hi>deſign</hi> of this Revelation, which doth <hi>make</hi> us <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>interest</hi> us in Him as our <hi>Saviour. For I have given them the words which thou gavest me, and they have received them, and have known ſurely that I came out from thee, and they have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that thou didst ſend me,</hi> John 17.8.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. <hi>In that it is a ſpecial effect and fruit of the Holy Spirit of God. I will give them an Heart to know me, that I am the Lord, and they ſhall be my People, and I will be their God, for they ſhall return unto me with their whole Heart,</hi> Jer. 24.7. <hi>Wherefore I give you to underſtand, that no Man ſpeaking by the Spirit of God, calleth Jeſus, accurſed, and that no Man can ſay that Jeſus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghost,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.3. Tho' the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41276:9"/> Lord Jeſus doth not oblige himſelf not to give forth the ſpecial Influences of his Holy Spirit to any, but in and with their ſerious uſing their natural Abilities, and the common aſſiſtances of the Spirit generally afforded, in thoſe ways he hath appointed, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Peoples partaking of his ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Aids and Bleſſings, yet he <hi>obliges us</hi> thus to make uſe of the <hi>means</hi> he hath <hi>ordained;</hi> and we have not any reaſon to expect theſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural effects any other way. When he does <hi>extraordinarily,</hi> and out of his common and <hi>Inſtituted</hi> way, work on, awaken, convince, and effectually convert Sinners, as he did <hi>Saul,</hi> when Travelling on ſuch a wretchedly wicked deſign towards <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> he does it not as <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Ruler,</hi> but as <hi>abſolute Lord.</hi> And when we find our ſelves ſo inlightned, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully wrought on, in the uſe of <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted means,</hi> that we are effectually determined to yield up our ſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely to Chriſt, as our Lord, this <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> is from the <hi>ſpecial influence of the Holy Spirit,</hi> and muſt be <hi>attributed</hi> unto <hi>Him.</hi> Faith is the gift of God,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41276:9"/> tho' ordinarily conferred along with out making uſe of the natural Powers we are endued with in the ways and methods inſtituted for this end, as reading and hearing the Word, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There is no na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <hi>connexion</hi> between our employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our natural Abilities and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in theſe ways, and this <hi>happy effect,</hi> for God hath not obliged himſelf to beſtow <hi>this Bleſſing</hi> by the Rules and Laws he hath eſtabliſhed to obſerve, in the ordinary way of his Providence, in ordering and governing the World, ſo far as doth concern and relate to Man. The <hi>connexion</hi> between them is purely <hi>Gracious,</hi> by virtue of the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Rules</hi> He hath <hi>fixed</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by, in the <hi>diſpenſation of his Grace.</hi> We may by that <hi>concurrence</hi> God affords in the way of his <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Providence,</hi> attain to as great a meaſure of ſpeculative, notional, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſive <hi>knowledge</hi> of what the Goſpel doth teach, as we can of thoſe matters which are treated of in <hi>other Books,</hi> provided we do <hi>proportionably</hi> apply our <hi>Study</hi> to them. But when in our uſing our natural Abilities theſe ways,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41276:10"/> we are brought to cloſe unfeignedly with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>yield</hi> up our ſelves <hi>entirely</hi> to his <hi>Conduct,</hi> this is owing to a <hi>divine Influence</hi> vouchſafed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>ordinary courſe</hi> of <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and is from God's proceeding with us according to his <hi>Law of Grace.</hi> Tho' we cannot apprehend in what way the Spirit doth <hi>effect,</hi> and bring about this excellent and happy <hi>change</hi> in us, ſo as certainly to <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> what is done by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> from what is done by our <hi>natural Abilities</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operating; yet we know by the <hi>effect</hi> that He hath exerted his <hi>wonderful Power,</hi> and to Him muſt all the <hi>Glory</hi> be <hi>aſcribed,</hi> who is the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal agent</hi> in this buſineſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. <hi>In the ſingular and ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Benefits which do accrue unto us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our thus knowing of Christ Jeſus.</hi> Of which Benefits I will now name but theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God's juſtifying of us, and own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to be in the Covenant of Grace.</hi> By Juſtification I do mean ſomething more than his Pardoning all our paſt Sins, even a <hi>change</hi> of our <hi>State,</hi> his acquitting and diſcharging us from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41276:10"/> the <hi>Law of Works,</hi> as a <hi>Covenant of Life.</hi> Were all my Sins freely par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and I left under the Law of Works, this <hi>Pardon</hi> would not <hi>avail</hi> me any thing, if my <hi>Life</hi> were at all <hi>continued,</hi> for my very next <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances</hi> would fall ſo <hi>ſhort</hi> of what that <hi>Law requires,</hi> I ſhould immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately be in the <hi>ſame ſtate</hi> I was in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my <hi>Pardon.</hi> We are all under the Law of Works till we do ſo know Chriſt Jeſus, as to yield up our ſelves unreſervedly unto his Conduct. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, we are not now ſo under the Law of Works, as our firſt Parents were immediately on their <hi>Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and before that <hi>gracious Promiſe</hi> that <hi>the Seed of the Woman ſhould break the Serpent's head,</hi> was given them, for till then they were purely under the Law of Works, and had no <hi>remedying Law</hi> to make uſe of for their <hi>Relief.</hi> We are naturally ſtill under that Law of Works, only we have this <hi>advantage,</hi> that now there is a Law of Pardon, or a <hi>remedying Law concurrent</hi> with it, if we will make uſe of it. But till we comply with, and accept of that Law, <hi>i. e.</hi> do
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41276:11"/> yield up our ſelves abſolutely to <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the other Law ſtands in full force againſt us.</p>
            <p>Our ſo knowing of <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> as hath been mentioned, is our <hi>actual conſenting</hi> to the <hi>gracious tender</hi> and <hi>offer</hi> God hath made to all Sinners, without excepting any, whereby we come to be really in the <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> What is ordinarily called the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> is only the <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Teſtament</hi> which Chriſt hath made of the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> or the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings</hi> he will beſtow on all thoſe who do or ſhall <hi>unfeignedly conſent</hi> to yield up themſelves <hi>abſolutely to Him.</hi> It is a <hi>Covenant</hi> only with thoſe who do thus <hi>conſent</hi> unto <hi>it.</hi> And upon our <hi>giving</hi> up our ſelves thus to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> God owns us to be in Covenant with Him. Of this <hi>Covenant Christ Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Mediator,</hi> to whom it pertains to ſee, that <hi>both parts</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> thus conſented to be <hi>performed.</hi> We are to do what is aſſigned to us, <hi>i. e.</hi> we muſt <hi>follow Chriſt's Conduct</hi> in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing we ſhall <hi>know</hi> he hath <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained</hi> for <hi>us,</hi> and therefore muſt uſe our <hi>honeſt endeavours</hi> to underſtand
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41276:11"/> what he hath <hi>taught;</hi> and upon our doing <hi>ſo,</hi> we come to be <hi>entitled</hi> to the <hi>Benefits God</hi> hath <hi>promiſed,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> is alſo to ſee <hi>accompliſhed,</hi> and made <hi>good</hi> unto <hi>us.</hi> When we know <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> a right, we are <hi>delivered from the power of darkneſs, and tranſlated into the Kingdom of his dear Son,</hi> Col. 1.13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Power to perform ſuch Obedience as God will graciouſly accept.</hi> This <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> which is a ſpecial effect of the Holy Spirit, is not a <hi>dead notion,</hi> but the <hi>Light of Life,</hi> a divine <hi>vital principle,</hi> which hath an <hi>influence</hi> on all the <hi>Powers</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> and <hi>Faculties</hi> of the <hi>whole Man,</hi> ſpiriting and directing them all in a <hi>good meaſure,</hi> in ways ſuitable to its own <hi>Nature,</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> for which it is <hi>given.</hi> It poſſeſſeth the Soul with a predominant <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>Christ,</hi> and influences the Perſon to <hi>labour</hi> after a <hi>Conformity</hi> to Him. It puts the Perſon upon conſidering and enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what things <hi>He,</hi> whom he hath taken for his <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>revealed,</hi> what he doth Command, and in what manner it <hi>behoves</hi> him, now he hath thus <hi>reſigned</hi> himſelf to Him, to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41276:12"/> himſelf; and it furniſhes him with <hi>ability</hi> to execute the ſame, by <hi>deriving</hi> freſh ſupplies of <hi>ſtrength</hi> from that <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> who is the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of this divine <hi>vital Principle.</hi> It diſpoſeth and enclineth him to do thoſe <hi>good Works</hi> Chriſt hath <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> him, and to uſe thoſe <hi>means</hi> Chriſt hath enjoyned, in order to his receiving greater meaſures of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of the Holy Spirit, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. Such a Perſon's Good Works and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience are <hi>accepted</hi> with God, not becauſe of their <hi>intrinſick worth,</hi> but only for the <hi>merit</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who hath <hi>procured the Law of Grace,</hi> and is the <hi>mediator</hi> of the <hi>new Covenant.</hi> Our beſt Works cannot merit Salvation, that is the <hi>purchaſe</hi> of <hi>Christ's Blood.</hi> We are juſtified and ſaved by <hi>Faith,</hi> and that is the <hi>Gift</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> ſo that we have nothing to <hi>boaſt of,</hi> tho very much for which we are to be <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi> Our <hi>good Works</hi> are an <hi>evidence</hi> of the <hi>truth</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> and that our <hi>knowledge</hi> of Chriſt is of the <hi>right kind:</hi> And ſuch is the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God</hi> through <hi>Christ,</hi> that the <hi>more</hi> we <hi>abound</hi> in them, the <hi>greater</hi> ſhall our
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41276:12"/> 
               <hi>Reward</hi> be; not becauſe of their <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> but becauſe of his <hi>gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> aſſigning <hi>degrees of Glory,</hi> in proportion to our <hi>abounding</hi> in <hi>new Obedience.</hi> We do not derive <hi>Power</hi> from Chriſt to <hi>merit</hi> any thing for our ſelves, but we receive from Him <hi>Power</hi> to perform ſuch <hi>Obedience</hi> as ſhall for <hi>his ſake</hi> be <hi>accepted</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded.</hi> Upon our performing ſuch <hi>Obedience,</hi> we ſhall receive <hi>freely</hi> the <hi>Bleſſings He</hi> hath <hi>merited,</hi> and which for his ſake are made over to us in the <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> Our <hi>Works</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> do not <hi>make</hi> us <hi>Righteous</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> but they prove and diſcover us to be <hi>ſo, i. e.</hi> that we are endu'd with a <hi>divine Principle,</hi> have our <hi>Natures changed,</hi> and do <hi>know Christ Jeſus aright,</hi> as <hi>vital acts</hi> do not <hi>make</hi> a <hi>living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> but they prove that the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> which performs them, hath a <hi>principle of Life</hi> from which thoſe <hi>acts</hi> do <hi>flow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4thly. Another excellency of this knowledge is, that <hi>it puts a check to vain Curioſity, to a ſearch after empty and leſs neceſſary Speculations, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41276:13"/> us from all carnal and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Confidence, and engages us to a commendable Diligence, by determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our enquiries after ſuch things as are moſt certain and true in themſelves, and will be moſt uſeful and profitable unto us, by advancing us both in intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual and moral Accompliſhments and Perfections.</hi> For it obliges us to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy our honeſt and beſt endeavours to <hi>underſtand,</hi> and make a <hi>right uſe</hi> of what <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> hath <hi>taught</hi> and <hi>revealed;</hi> which are matters of ſuch <hi>excellency,</hi> that all <hi>other things</hi> are of <hi>little account</hi> with thoſe who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>importance</hi> of <hi>theſe,</hi> as the Apoſtle plainly teſtified, when he ſaid, he accounted all things <hi>but loſs,</hi> &amp;c. Which brings me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> What account he who knows <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> aright doth make of all other things. The <hi>Sence</hi> a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtian hath of the <hi>excellency</hi> of this <hi>knowledge,</hi> diſcovers it ſelf in the great <hi>alteration</hi> it makes in his <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> of all other things from what they were before. He doth ſet now a <hi>just eſtimate</hi> upon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41276:13"/> all <hi>worldly Enjoyments,</hi> and <hi>outward Privileges</hi> relating to <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal performances</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſeveral Natures, Places, and Ranks, to their uſe and ends. He does not abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them, as evil in themſelves, or as altogether uſeleſs to any good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, for ſhould he <hi>do ſo,</hi> he would be <hi>faulty.</hi> He owns them to be the <hi>good Gifts</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that a very <hi>good uſe</hi> may be made of them, is <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> to God for them, if he enjoys them, and <hi>praiſeth God</hi> for beſtowing them on others. He acknowledges they have a <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in their <hi>proper place</hi> and <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> But then he eſteems them as the Apoſtle did, as <hi>altogether uſeleſs</hi> to the <hi>buſineſs</hi> here ſpoken of, <hi>viz.</hi> to be the matter of our Confidence, yea, extreamly <hi>hurtful</hi> when depended on for Juſtification. To be but <hi>loſs,</hi> yea <hi>dung</hi> when compar'd with, and ſet in oppoſition to this <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> which hath an <hi>excellency</hi> in it, unſpeakably greater than all other things have, and which alone can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail and profit us to <hi>Juſtification</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41276:14"/> 
               <hi>Salvation,</hi> That <hi>divine Light</hi> which diſcovers <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> to a Perſon, as the Perſon commiſſioned by God to be the Saviour of Sinners, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally cauſeth him, from a ſence of his own Sin and Guilt, to yield up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf entirely to Him, to be ſaved by Him in his own way, doth diſcover all other things to him in ſuch a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>diſparaging manner,</hi> that he plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceives they cannot bear any <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion</hi> with <hi>Christ;</hi> and therefore he accounts them to be <hi>loſs,</hi> as to the buſineſs of <hi>Juſtification.</hi> If I do not eſteem Chriſt Jeſus worthy enough to be the <hi>ſole object</hi> of my <hi>dependance,</hi> I do <hi>not know him aright.</hi> And if I ſet up any thing in the World, as that I will truſt to, and depend on for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually with Him, I acknowledge a greater, or an equal virtue and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in that, with what I pretend to believe is in Chriſt for this purpoſe. Or if I depend on any thing together with Chriſt, tho' in an <hi>inferiour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,</hi> I do not take him to be the <hi>only and all ſufficient Saviour of Sinners,</hi> and ſo have not that knowledge of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41276:14"/> Chriſt Jeſus here ſpoken of. Indeed, there are <hi>other things</hi> we may <hi>depend on,</hi> and make the <hi>ground</hi> of our <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion</hi> and <hi>Confidence,</hi> that we are <hi>Juſtified</hi> and ſhall be <hi>Saved,</hi> as thoſe which are <hi>ſure, certain,</hi> and <hi>never-failing Evidences</hi> of our <hi>Interest</hi> in <hi>Christ,</hi> as our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and that we do know Him aright. But there is not any thing but <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> we may truſt to, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on for <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, i. e.</hi> as <hi>that,</hi> for the <hi>ſake of which</hi> we ſhall be Juſtified and Saved.</p>
            <p>From what hath been diſcourſed we may take notice,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That Perſons may have great Meaſures of ſpeculative Knowledge concerning Christ Jeſus, and what he hath taught, and not be True Chriſtians.</hi> The Apoſtle indeed doth tell us, that <hi>whoſoever believeth that Jeſus is the Christ, is born of God,</hi> which is the ſame with his being a <hi>True Chriſtian,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. but it is evident, beyond all doubt, by his following diſcourſe, that he doth not ſpeak of a bare <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41276:15"/> Knowledge,</hi> but of ſuch a Knowledge and Faith as I have been giving an account of. Such a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or Belief that Jeſus is the Chriſt, that is, the <hi>Perſon God hath commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to be the Saviour of Sinners,</hi> as doth effectually cauſe a Perſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign up himſelf entirely to Him, doth <hi>conſtitute</hi> him a <hi>True Chriſtian.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Knowledge or Faith People may have, which falls ſhort of this, will not profit them to <hi>Juſtification,</hi> nor have a due effect and influence on their Lives. The moſt <hi>pompous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi> will not prevail for our <hi>accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where this is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22, 23. Therefore,</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>We ought to make a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough and impartial ſearch concerning our ſelves, whether we be true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> Whether we are ſo fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that <hi>Jeſus is the Christ,</hi> that we do <hi>ſincerely</hi> yield up our ſelves, without any <hi>reſervation</hi> to follow his <hi>Conduct.</hi> It is not enough that we call our ſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>pretend</hi> to own him for our <hi>Lord,</hi> as <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22, 23. diſcovers. But we muſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the <hi>Truth</hi> of our owning him to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41276:15"/> be <hi>our Lord,</hi> by employing our ſelves heartily to <hi>understand</hi> what He hath taught, and to <hi>believe,</hi> and make <hi>ſuch uſe</hi> of what we attain to <hi>know</hi> He hath <hi>taught,</hi> as we ſhall perceive he intends and appoints. For,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Tho' a right knowledge of this one point, that Jeſus is the Christ, doth conſtitute and make a Perſon a Chriſtian; yet there are many points Jeſus Christ hath taught and revealed, which every ſincere Chriſtian is indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſibly obliged to endeavour to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and make a due uſe of.</hi> When a Perſon becomes a True Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, he doth reſign himſelf (as you have been told) entirely unto <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> as his <hi>Lord,</hi> and obligeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, without any reſervation, to uſe his <hi>ſerious, honest,</hi> and <hi>ſincere endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours</hi> to know what he hath revealed, and to <hi>aſſent</hi> unto, and make <hi>ſuch uſe</hi> of what he ſhall attain to <hi>know</hi> he hath <hi>revealed,</hi> as the <hi>nature,</hi> or <hi>particular intendment</hi> thereof (ſo far as he ſhall know the ſame) doth <hi>direct.</hi> He doth not <hi>capitulate</hi> and <hi>compound</hi> with <hi>Christ,</hi> that he will aſſent unto, and make ſuch uſe as he orders, of <hi>just</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41276:16"/> ſuch a <hi>number</hi> of <hi>Articles,</hi> but will be excus'd from concerning himſelf to <hi>extend</hi> his <hi>knowledge,</hi> or <hi>practice</hi> any <hi>further.</hi> It is out of my <hi>Reach</hi> (and I am perſwaded it is out of the reach of any Man, or Body of Men) to aſſign a <hi>preciſe number</hi> of <hi>Articles</hi> which are neceſſary to be <hi>explicitly known</hi> and believed by all <hi>ſincere Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>beyond</hi> which no Chriſtian is obliged to endeavour to <hi>proceed</hi> in his <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi> Peoples <hi>Capacities, Opportunities,</hi> and <hi>Advantages</hi> are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>various</hi> and <hi>different.</hi> Many things may be <hi>neceſſary</hi> for ſome Chriſtians to <hi>believe,</hi> which are not <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be believed by <hi>others;</hi> becauſe ſome do attain to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them, and a great many more may never attain to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them, and this not becauſe of any <hi>faulty omiſſion</hi> or <hi>neglect</hi> to uſe their <hi>honest endeavours</hi> to underſtand what <hi>Christ</hi> hath made known to the World, but from <hi>ſomething elſe</hi> which will not be <hi>reckoned</hi> to them for a <hi>fault.</hi> I think a certain number of Articles cannot be fixed on (beſides this, that Jeſus is the Chriſt) which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41276:16"/> we may <hi>peremptorily</hi> determine muſt of neceſſity be explicitely known and believed, or <hi>no Perſon can be ſaved.</hi> For the <hi>belief</hi> of the other <hi>Doctrines</hi> Chriſt hath <hi>taught,</hi> doth not <hi>conſtitute</hi> or <hi>make</hi> a Perſon a <hi>True Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps ſome may be now ready to ſay, <hi>that's well,</hi> for then we are <hi>ſafe</hi> tho' we be <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and continue <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi> of all the <hi>Doctrines</hi> Chriſt hath <hi>taught,</hi> beſides this, that <hi>Jeſus is the Christ;</hi> or if we ſhould come to know them we are <hi>ſafe,</hi> tho' we refuſe to <hi>believe</hi> them, and make that <hi>uſe</hi> of them Chriſt <hi>appoints;</hi> for we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve moſt firmly that <hi>Jeſus is the Christ,</hi> and ſo we are <hi>True Chriſtians,</hi> and therefore <hi>ſafe,</hi> and need not <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> our ſelves about <hi>knowing</hi> or <hi>belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> any thing more.</p>
            <p>Nay, now you are <hi>out,</hi> moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly and wretchedly <hi>out.</hi> Believe as much as you <hi>can,</hi> beſides this <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> your belief will not make you a <hi>True Chriſtian.</hi> It is the <hi>right know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> or belief of this <hi>Article,</hi> that <hi>Jeſus is the Christ,</hi> that <hi>makes</hi> a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a <hi>True Chriſtian.</hi> But the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving of <hi>this,</hi> doth not <hi>exclude</hi> your
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41276:17"/> believing of other <hi>Articles,</hi> or <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge</hi> you from any obligation to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>other points,</hi> or make your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving of other matters <hi>needleſs.</hi> But it brings you under an <hi>indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable obligation</hi> to endeavour to know and believe <hi>more.</hi> Tho' the belief of other points is not <hi>neceſſary</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a Perſon a <hi>True Chriſtian,</hi> yet <hi>other things</hi> are <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be <hi>believed</hi> by <hi>him that is a True Chriſtian.</hi> The true Chriſtian is obliged to uſe his beſt endeavours to know what Chriſt hath revealed, and to aſſent unto, and make a right uſe of what he attains to know Chriſt hath revealed. And if you do not do <hi>thus,</hi> you do not <hi>approve</hi> your ſelves <hi>True Chriſtians,</hi> you do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit your ſelves as true Chriſtians ought, and muſt acquit themſelves. If you either <hi>neglect</hi> to <hi>enquire</hi> after, and to uſe your honeſt endeavours to know what Chriſt hath revealed, or <hi>refuſe</hi> to <hi>aſſent</hi> to and make a <hi>good uſe</hi> of what you <hi>know</hi> he hath <hi>revealed,</hi> you have juſt reaſon to <hi>conclude</hi> you are not <hi>True Chriſtians,</hi> and do not <hi>know</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>aright,</hi> whatever you affirm in your words.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:41276:17"/>
            <p>There are many things Chriſt hath taught and revealed ſo <hi>plainly,</hi> ſo <hi>clearly,</hi> ſo <hi>diſtinctly,</hi> you cannot but know <hi>ſome</hi> of them, if you <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> endeavour to know what He hath <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed;</hi> and what you know he hath revealed, you muſt aſſent to and <hi>make uſe of,</hi> if you do <hi>rightly know</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Him to be the only Saviour of Sinners.</p>
            <p>If it be now ask'd what are thoſe particular Points or Articles Chriſt hath revealed, which are neceſſary for Chriſtians to endeavour to know, and which being known to be revealed by Him they muſt indiſpenſably aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to, and make uſe of: I anſwer, that what Chriſt hath revealed, is <hi>propounded</hi> to us in <hi>certain words</hi> which make diſtinct <hi>Sentences</hi> and <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> and being thus <hi>conſidered,</hi> they are <hi>objects</hi> of aſſent, and matters of <hi>Faith;</hi> tho' when we conſider tho nature of the Truths thus propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and their ſpecial Intendment, they may be conveniently reduced to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Heads,</hi> to which particular <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominations</hi> may be aſſign'd. Some of theſe I will name, together with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41276:18"/> ſome particular Propoſitions Chriſt hath taught, which properly belong to theſe Heads.</p>
            <p>As 1ſt. Thoſe Propoſitions which deſcribe his <hi>Perſon,</hi> and inſtruct us <hi>who he was,</hi> whom God did <hi>ſend</hi> and <hi>commiſſion</hi> to be the <hi>Saviour of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> As that <hi>He is God, the Son of God, the only begotten of the Father, God over all, bleſſed for ever,</hi> John 1. 1. Rom. 9.5. <hi>The Son of God,</hi> and the <hi>Meſſias</hi> are often uſed in the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> as <hi>Reciprocal Terms,</hi> not as if the <hi>ſtrict Idea,</hi> the term <hi>Meſſias,</hi> doth ſtand for, were the ſame <hi>the Son of God</hi> doth ſtand for, but becauſe <hi>He who is the Son of God</hi> is the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and He who is the <hi>Meſſias</hi> is the <hi>Son of God;</hi> both theſe Propoſitions I <hi>believe,</hi> becauſe I find that <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> and his Apoſtles, by <hi>his order,</hi> did reach <hi>them.</hi> I do not think that He was the <hi>Son of God</hi> becauſe He was the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> as the <hi>Socinians</hi> aſſert; nor yet, that He was the <hi>Meſſias</hi> becauſe He was the <hi>Son of God,</hi> as ſome affirm in oppoſition to the former, but that <hi>the Son of God</hi> was the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Father</hi> did not <hi>think fit</hi> to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41276:18"/> 
               <hi>commiſſion</hi> any but his <hi>own Son</hi> to be the <hi>Saviour of Sinners.</hi> When a true Chriſtian underſtands that Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus hath taught that <hi>He is God,</hi> He muſt aſſent unto it, and endeavour to uſe it for the nouriſhing, ſtrengthening, and confirming of his <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Him.</hi> To aſſure him that He is <hi>all-ſufficient</hi> to fulfil the Work He hath <hi>undertaken,</hi> and to which He is <hi>commiſſioned.</hi> And to direct and juſtifie his <hi>paying Divine Honour and Worſhip</hi> to <hi>Him.</hi> So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that He <hi>was made Fleſh,</hi> did aſſume our whole Nature, and was true Man, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.31. which may ſatisfie us, that He was in a <hi>Condition</hi> and <hi>Fitneſs</hi> for that part of His <hi>Work</hi> which did conſiſt in His <hi>Suffering</hi> in our <hi>ſtead</hi> and on our <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half;</hi> and that He hath a moſt <hi>tender</hi> and <hi>compaſſionate concern</hi> for <hi>us,</hi> whoſe Nature He did <hi>aſſume,</hi> Heb. 2.14. Heb. 4.15.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, Thoſe Propoſitions which acquaint us with the <hi>occaſion</hi> of His undertaking this <hi>Office,</hi> and being commiſſioned to <hi>it.</hi> As, that by the <hi>Fall of our firſt Parents, ſin entred into the World.</hi> That <hi>we are all fallen ſhort
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41276:19"/> of the Glory of God.</hi> And <hi>that we are by Nature the Children of Wrath,</hi> Rom. 3.23. Rom. 5.12. Eph. 2.3. which may convince us more through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of our great <hi>need</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> make us have more <hi>low</hi> and <hi>humble thoughts</hi> of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and inſpire us with moſt <hi>admiring and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated gratitude</hi> and thankfulneſs, to and for <hi>Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3dly, Thoſe Propoſitions which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us that the ſending of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour did proceed and ſpring purely from the <hi>Free Grace, Mercy, and Love of God. God ſo loved the World that He gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting life,</hi> &amp;c. John 3.16, 17. 1 John 4.9. Eph. 2.4. to the 9th. This is proper to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our <hi>Admiration</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi> Here is room for our exerting them in their <hi>fulleſt</hi> ſtrength and <hi>force.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4thly, Thoſe Propoſitions which teach us in what ways, and by what ſteps He did, and doth execute, and will finally accompliſh the <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>Office</hi> He <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertook.</hi> As, 1. By <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing the Father, and making His
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41276:19"/> Will known to the World,</hi> John 1.18. Heb. 1.1, 2. John 15.15. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are <hi>furniſhed</hi> with the moſt <hi>uſeful, pertinent, neceſſary</hi> and <hi>profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Inſtructions;</hi> do know where we are to employ our <hi>Searches</hi> and <hi>Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> to the <hi>beſt purpoſe:</hi> And what we may without <hi>fluctuation, doubt,</hi> or <hi>wavering,</hi> and with the <hi>greateſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence entertain,</hi> and <hi>depend</hi> upon for their <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly, By <hi>fulfilling all Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>leading the moſt Innocent, unble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh'd, exact and holy Life,</hi> Mat. 3.15. 1 Pet. 2.21. Acts 10.38. Thus He has ſet us an <hi>Example</hi> in His own <hi>Life.</hi> Hath viſibly commended and diſcovered the <hi>amiableneſs</hi> of what He <hi>Commands</hi> and <hi>Enjoyns.</hi> And hath ſhewn us in the moſt convincing and obliging <hi>way,</hi> how we ought to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean</hi> and behave our ſelves. And hereby we perceive that He was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably fitted for <hi>another part</hi> of what pertained to Him in His Eſtate of <hi>Humiliation,</hi> viz. making Himſelf a Sacrifice for our ſins, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, <hi>By ſuffering very many hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, innumerable reproaches, and indignities, enduring the Wrath of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41276:20"/> God, and actually dying in open view as a Malefactor on the Croſs, offering up himſelf a Sacrifice to ſatisfie Divine Juſtice for the ſins of the World, and giving his Soul a Ranſom for Sinners,</hi> Acts 2.23. and 36. Heb. 9.26. 1 Pet. 3.18. 1 Tim. 2.6. which diſcovers the moſt <hi>execrable</hi> nature of <hi>Sin,</hi> how extreamly loathſom and <hi>hateful</hi> it is to <hi>God,</hi> and therefore ſhould be <hi>ſo</hi> to <hi>us.</hi> This manifeſts the <hi>Condeſcention</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> of Chriſt to <hi>us,</hi> in the moſt <hi>affecting manner</hi> that can be <hi>imagined.</hi> And is the moſt <hi>potent</hi> Argument to <hi>kindle</hi> and <hi>excite</hi> the trueſt <hi>Love</hi> in our Souls to <hi>Him,</hi> and calls for our exerting <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>Him</hi> in its moſt <hi>powerful actings,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.14.15.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, By <hi>riſing again from the dead the third day,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.4. Rom. 1.4. Rom. 4.25. Hereby the <hi>Prophecies</hi> which were before concerning Him, and His own <hi>Predictions</hi> were moſt <hi>exactly</hi> verified and <hi>fulfilled.</hi> This gives a moſt certain undeniable <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> that His Sacrificing of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his <hi>Death</hi> were accepted of <hi>God,</hi> and are <hi>prevalent</hi> for all the <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes</hi> for which they were <hi>intended.</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:41276:20"/> T'is ſtrengthens <hi>our Faith and Hope in</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> And aſſures us of the <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi> of our <hi>Reſurrection</hi> at the <hi>end of the World,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.21. Rom. 8.11.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, By <hi>Aſcending up into Heaven in the ſight of His Diſciples</hi> (after He had given full proof of the truth of His Reſurrection, and commiſſioned them to Preach His Goſpel to all the World) <hi>That there He may in His exalted Eſtate, perform what further per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains unto Him as the Saviour of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> Mark 16.19. This aſſures us of the efficacy and prevalence of His <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> and the ſolid <hi>ground</hi> we have to <hi>depend</hi> upon <hi>Him</hi> for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever He hath <hi>warranted</hi> us to <hi>ask</hi> in His <hi>Name,</hi> and <hi>expect</hi> from <hi>Him,</hi> Heb. 7.14, 15. John 14.1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="6">6thly, By <hi>ſending and giving forth the Holy Spirit for the purpoſes and ends for which He hath promiſed Him,</hi> viz. for the making of His Word and Ordinances effectual, for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Sinners, and the Edification and Comfort of true Believers, <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 17, and 26. And here by the way we may take notice, that He hath taught how we are to conceive of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41276:21"/> the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> certifying that <hi>He is God,</hi> Acts 5.3, 4. 2 Cor. 3.16, 17. Now when a true Chriſtian under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands, that <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> hath given this account of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> He is as <hi>much obliged</hi> to believe it, as He is to believe that <hi>Jeſus is the Christ;</hi> and when he underſtands that Chriſt hath taught that the <hi>Father, Himſelf,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> are God, that He ſaith ſuch things of <hi>them,</hi> and requires ſuch <hi>Homage</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> to be paid unto <hi>them,</hi> as are <hi>peculiar</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> and certifies that theſe <hi>Three</hi> are <hi>One,</hi> (Matth. 28.19. 1 John 5.7.) He is obliged to aſſent unto and believe this <hi>Truth,</hi> as well as any thing elſe that Chriſt hath <hi>taught.</hi> It is as hard for me to reconcile a Perſons denying, or not believing <hi>this,</hi> when he knows that Chriſt Jeſus hath taught <hi>it,</hi> with his being a <hi>ſincere Christian,</hi> or having <hi>unreſervedly reſigned himſelf up to Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as any Man can pretend it is to him, to tell how <hi>theſe three can be God,</hi> and yet there be but <hi>one God.</hi> I believe that the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are God, becauſe I find that <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> hath taught <hi>ſo.</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:41276:21"/> And if any Man can pretend he hath ground to believe this <hi>Article</hi> to be <hi>falſe,</hi> or to <hi>with-hold</hi> his <hi>aſſent,</hi> when he knows that Jeſus Chriſt hath <hi>taught it,</hi> he cannot with <hi>colour,</hi> pretend he has juſt reaſon to believe that <hi>Jeſus is the Meſſias,</hi> nor to believe any <hi>one point</hi> upon his <hi>Authority.</hi> For if we queſtion the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>any thing</hi> we <hi>know</hi> He <hi>taught,</hi> we have the like <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to <hi>queſtion</hi> the Truth of <hi>every thing</hi> He taught. He that is upon ſuch <hi>Terms,</hi> can hardly deſerve to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a <hi>true Chriſtian.</hi> He muſt be <hi>extraordinarily ſoft</hi> and <hi>favourable</hi> to himſelf, if he can <hi>perſuade himſelf</hi> that is <hi>one.</hi> If I were not fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> underſtood the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> and knew how to <hi>ſpeak</hi> of <hi>it,</hi> better than any <hi>meer Man,</hi> I ſhould not take him to be <hi>my Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour.</hi> It may be ſome will ſay, they do believe what <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> hath <hi>taught,</hi> but they cannot believe the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Trinity</hi> as it is taught in certain <hi>Creeds,</hi> which are but of <hi>Humane Compoſure.</hi> To ſuch I would <hi>ſay,</hi> if you really know, and heartily believe all that Chriſt hath
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41276:22"/> taught <hi>concerning this matter,</hi> it is as much as I can <hi>deſire,</hi> and as much, as you <hi>ought to believe concerning it.</hi> But tho' other words are now ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily uſed in teaching of this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> than are uſed about it in the <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> yet the Doctrine is but the <hi>ſame</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> taught. The <hi>other Words</hi> and <hi>Terms</hi> which are now uſed, do not <hi>add any thing</hi> to <hi>his Doctrine;</hi> they were not originally intended to make the <hi>Doctrine</hi> more <hi>perfect</hi> than Chriſt delivered it. The Doctrine continued as it was taught in the Holy Scriptures, till ſome <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous</hi> (not to ſay malicious) Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aſſumed to themſelves to <hi>affix</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſiniſter Interpretation</hi> and <hi>Conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to the <hi>Words of Chriſt,</hi> as did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly <hi>alter</hi> His <hi>Doctrine,</hi> very much <hi>depreciating Chriſt</hi> Himſelf and the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> degrading <hi>Chriſt</hi> into a <hi>meer Man</hi> (though He Himſelf taught that He was God) and teaching that the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> was but the <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Virtue</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and not <hi>God.</hi> When this <hi>Method</hi> was uſed to <hi>corrupt</hi> the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſincere Chriſtians found it <hi>expedient</hi> to make uſe of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41276:22"/> 
               <hi>other Words,</hi> which have been <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively</hi> retained. But they uſed not <hi>theſe words,</hi> with a deſign to teach <hi>more</hi> than Chriſt had taught, only to deliver what He had taught, with a <hi>denial of that corrupt Senſe</hi> falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers had <hi>ſtampt</hi> upon <hi>His Words.</hi> So that the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> as it is ordinarily taught amongſt us, is no other, than that the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are God, as Chriſt hath taught they are, and that we do reject that <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Conſtruction,</hi> which Men of their <hi>own Heads,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>Authority</hi> have affixed to <hi>Chriſt's Doctrine.</hi> It is but the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine Chriſt</hi> hath taught, with an <hi>oppoſition</hi> to, and <hi>denial</hi> of that <hi>Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Words,</hi> and <hi>Diminution</hi> of <hi>Senſe,</hi> which other People had <hi>intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced</hi> touching that which Chriſt had <hi>taught.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſay that this Doctrine is <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> is in <hi>effect</hi> to <hi>deny</hi> that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is the Meſſias,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Can the <hi>Fountain</hi> of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> teach any thing that is <hi>contrary to Reaſon?</hi> Does not the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> He that was <hi>commiſſioned</hi> to <hi>teach</hi> Men the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41276:23"/> 
               <hi>Mind of God,</hi> know what is <hi>conſonant</hi> to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> better than we <hi>do?</hi> It is not to be expected that People ſhould in <hi>good earneſt</hi> believe this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> till they are fully perſuaded that <hi>Jeſus is the Chriſt,</hi> and when they heartily believe <hi>that,</hi> there can be no ground to deny their aſſent to <hi>this,</hi> or any other <hi>Doctrine,</hi> they know he hath taught. We have this notice by <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Revelation,</hi> that the <hi>Father is God,</hi> and that the <hi>Son is God,</hi> and that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt is God,</hi> which we could not know by the <hi>meer Light of Nature.</hi> Now if thoſe who ſay this Doctrine is againſt and contrary to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> do mean no more, than that they find <hi>Christ</hi> hath <hi>revealed it,</hi> but they <hi>cannot underſtand</hi> any more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>it,</hi> than what He hath <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed,</hi> they are in the <hi>right,</hi> but they would do <hi>well,</hi> to expreſs their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by <hi>decent and proper Terms,</hi> which may ſignifie the <hi>Senſe</hi> they have of their <hi>own</hi> and Humane <hi>weakneſs,</hi> and not <hi>throw</hi> Unworthy and <hi>Blaſphemous Aſperſions</hi> on a moſt <hi>certain Divine Truth</hi> and <hi>Doctrine.</hi> He that heartily believes that <hi>Jeſus is the Chriſt,</hi> and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41276:23"/> takes Him <hi>unfeignedly</hi> for his <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour,</hi> will believe whatſoever <hi>he knows Christ</hi> hath <hi>taught,</hi> and will be <hi>contented</hi> to wait to <hi>know more</hi> than He hath <hi>taught</hi> concerning any <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle,</hi> till <hi>He</hi> ſhall be <hi>pleaſed</hi> to make a <hi>further diſcovery</hi> of it. Our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> who is <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed,</hi> is <hi>God,</hi> affords us great <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> to depend upon Him for, and to <hi>expect</hi> from Him <hi>Aids</hi> and <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſistances ſuitable</hi> to our <hi>occaſions,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Influences</hi> as will render our <hi>duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful labours,</hi> and endeavours <hi>proſperous</hi> and <hi>ſucceſsful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7thly; By <hi>coming at the end of the World in unconceivable Glory, at which time He will raiſe the dead, judge the World, and render to every one according to his Works,</hi> Acts 10.42. Acts 17.32. 2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>This,</hi> if any thing, ſhould keep us in a <hi>continual holy Awe</hi> of Him, and have a very <hi>powerful</hi> and good <hi>Influence</hi> upon our <hi>Conduct</hi> at all times, if we have any <hi>care</hi> for, or <hi>regard</hi> to our <hi>indiſputably</hi> greateſt <hi>Intereſts.</hi> And therefore true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould concern themſelves very much to underſtand as particularly as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41276:24"/> they can, and make a good uſe of what Chriſt hath taught relating to what I ſhall hint unto you in the next place.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, Thoſe Propoſitions which acquaint us with the <hi>Evil Acts</hi> and <hi>Vicious Inclinations</hi> and <hi>Luſts,</hi> He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires us to <hi>abstain</hi> from and <hi>mortifie;</hi> and the <hi>moral Duties</hi> He <hi>commands</hi> us to <hi>perform,</hi> as alſo in what manner it is His pleaſure we <hi>ſhould do them.</hi> Theſe are either <hi>general</hi> or <hi>particular:</hi> Thoſe that are <hi>general,</hi> oblige us to renounce all <hi>corrupt affections,</hi> and abſtain from every <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>Sin,</hi> and to exerciſe our ſelves in all the <hi>Duties</hi> we <hi>owe</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> our <hi>Neighbours,</hi> and <hi>our ſelves,</hi> without deſcending to mention particular inſtances, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging us to employ our enquiries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, that we obtain as <hi>distinct</hi> a knowledge of them as we can; ſuch are <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. Thoſe which are <hi>particular,</hi> do name cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Vices, Evil Acts,</hi> and <hi>Luſts</hi> we muſt carefully <hi>ſhun</hi> and <hi>avoid,</hi> and <hi>ſubdue</hi> certain <hi>Graces, Virtues,</hi> and <hi>good Acts,</hi> we muſt employ ourſelves in. Theſe may be reduced to <hi>three
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41276:24"/> Heads,</hi> viz. Thoſe which concern <hi>all Chriſtians in common.</hi> Thoſe which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them according to the <hi>ſeveral Relations</hi> they ſtand in unto others. And thoſe which pertain to them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>various Eſtates and Conditions</hi> the Providence of God doth place them in. We ſhould endeavour to be as diſtinctly acquainted with theſe, as we can, that our <hi>Conduct</hi> may be <hi>Regular, Orderly,</hi> and <hi>Exact,</hi> and may <hi>beautifie</hi> and <hi>adorn</hi> our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</hi> Theſe make up the <hi>greateſt part</hi> of that <hi>Revelation</hi> Jeſus Chriſt hath made of the <hi>Will of God</hi> unto the <hi>World.</hi> Theſe are <hi>diſperſed</hi> through the <hi>whole Body</hi> of thoſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Records</hi> which contain the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries</hi> He hath made of the <hi>Father's Mind,</hi> ſo that we cannot attend to <hi>any page</hi> of the <hi>ſame,</hi> but we ſhall be ſure to meet with <hi>ſome of them.</hi> Amongſt all the things that <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> hath <hi>taught,</hi> theſe are the <hi>leaſt diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> but with <hi>profoundeſt Grief</hi> be it <hi>ſpoken,</hi> none are more <hi>neglected,</hi> and more <hi>contradicted</hi> in the <hi>Practices</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> of the Many.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:41276:25"/>6thly. Thoſe Propoſitions which relate what <hi>Privileges</hi> do pertain to them who do know <hi>Chriſt Jeſus aright,</hi> which acquaint us what <hi>Benefits, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages,</hi> and <hi>ineſtimable Bleſſings</hi> ſuch Perſons do partake of at <hi>preſent,</hi> and may further expect with good <hi>aſſurance</hi> both in <hi>this Life</hi> and the <hi>next.</hi> As that they partake of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> and are made his <hi>Temples,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.19. Rom. 8.9. Have all their Sins <hi>Pardoned,</hi> are <hi>Juſtified</hi> and admitted into the <hi>new Covenant,</hi> are <hi>Sanctified,</hi> and made partakers of <hi>the Divine Nature,</hi> Eph. 1.7. 1 Cor. 6.11. 2 Pet. 1.3, 4. Rom. 3.24. are made the <hi>Children of God,</hi> John 1.12. Gal. 3.26. Rom. 8.14, 15. Have the <hi>Holy Angels</hi> to Miniſter, and do many <hi>good Offices</hi> to them, Heb. 1.14. That all <hi>occurences,</hi> even the moſt <hi>afflicting</hi> that ſhall be ordered forth unto them, ſhall be <hi>over-ruled</hi> to their beſt <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi> Rom. 8.28. That their <hi>Bodies</hi> ſhall at the end of the World be raiſed <hi>Glorious Bodies,</hi> Phil. 3.21. And that they ſhall inherit <hi>Eternal Life</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> in the next World, and have their <hi>Glorious Recompences</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41276:25"/> in <hi>proportion</hi> to what they <hi>Suffer</hi> for the <hi>ſake of Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>improvement</hi> they make in their <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> unto Him at preſent, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.21, 34. Theſe things, and every thing elſe which Chriſt hath taught of the <hi>like Nature,</hi> are very proper and powerful <hi>Arguments</hi> to quicken us to, and <hi>animate</hi> us in the <hi>work</hi> and <hi>buſineſs</hi> He doth <hi>aſſign</hi> us, whilſt we continue in this <hi>World,</hi> and to ſupport and <hi>comfort</hi> us under all the <hi>Calamities</hi> and <hi>Sufferings</hi> that may befal us <hi>here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7thly. Thoſe Propoſitions which inform us what <hi>Ordinances</hi> He hath <hi>Inſtituted,</hi> and in what <hi>manner</hi> they are to be <hi>obſerved:</hi> As <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> the <hi>Ministry of the Word,</hi> and his <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> Matth. 28.19, 20. Eph. 4.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Matth. 26.27, 28. 1 Cor. 11.23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are appointed to be uſed as <hi>Pledges</hi> and <hi>Aſſurances</hi> of the <hi>Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Reſpect</hi> God hath to thoſe who <hi>heartily believe</hi> in <hi>Christ,</hi> as <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> of our <hi>Submiſſion</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> unto our <hi>Lord;</hi> and as <hi>means</hi> by which we are to receive <hi>greater meaſures</hi> of the <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Influences</hi> of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:41276:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> hath taught many <hi>Propoſitions</hi> relating to every one of theſe <hi>Heads,</hi> the knowing and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of <hi>which,</hi> will contribute much towards our arriving at as <hi>clear, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct,</hi> and <hi>full knowledge</hi> of theſe <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> as is <hi>expedient</hi> for us. And He hath taught very many Propoſitions which may be reduced more perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently to other Heads to which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Titles may be aſſigned. Yet,</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, Tho' there is not any thing Jeſus Chriſt hath taught, but it is <hi>most certainly true,</hi> and hath its <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per uſe;</hi> there are <hi>ſome things</hi> of more <hi>common</hi> and <hi>eminent Importance;</hi> the <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>which,</hi> hath a moſt plain, direct, and immediate <hi>tendency,</hi> to nouriſh and <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> our <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Him,</hi> to excite and maintain in us, <hi>Devout, Pious,</hi> and <hi>Divine Affections,</hi> and to aſſiſt and help us in <hi>forming</hi> our <hi>Converſations ſo,</hi> that they ſhall not only be <hi>Innocent,</hi> and <hi>without Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> but <hi>Exemplary,</hi> and <hi>worthy of imitation.</hi> And <hi>theſe</hi> are the <hi>matters</hi> a <hi>True Chriſtian</hi> ſhould in the <hi>first place,</hi> and principally endeavour to be acquainted with, tho' he is not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41276:26"/> to confine himſelf to them, but muſt labour to obtain the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of more, if he can, and to be continually growing in <hi>True Faith</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs of living.</hi> Therefore,</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, <hi>A good Collection</hi> of thoſe <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> which are of the greateſt <hi>moment</hi> to <hi>True Christians</hi> to have a <hi>good knowledge</hi> of, and which Chriſt and his Apoſtles did moſt of all <hi>inſiſt</hi> on, and peculiarly <hi>commend</hi> to Peoples <hi>ſpecial notice,</hi> will be of great <hi>uſe</hi> to True Chriſtians, in order to their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a more <hi>eaſie</hi> and ſpeedy <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> in matters which will be of <hi>notable uſe</hi> to them. Tho' we may not ſay to true Believers with reference to any <hi>certain number</hi> of <hi>Articles,</hi> as God Almighty doth to the <hi>Waves of the Sea, Thus far ſhall ye go, and no farther,</hi> nor poſitively determine that ſuch a number of Articles muſt <hi>of neceſſity</hi> be explicitely underſtood and believed by <hi>every</hi> True Chriſtian; yet their being provided with ſuch a <hi>Collection</hi> of <hi>Articles</hi> well atteſted by the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> would be very <hi>ſerviceable,</hi> and yield them much <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,</hi> if they have not a <hi>diſtinct
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41276:27"/> notional</hi> knowledge of them, before they are effectually brought to believe or know (in the manner before rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) that <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the Perſon God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and commiſſioned to be the <hi>only Saviour</hi> of Sinners. For,</p>
            <p n="6">6thly, This <hi>advantage</hi> doth accrue to People by their being <hi>early</hi> inſtructed in the Doctrines <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> hath taught, and obtaining a true <hi>notional knowledge</hi> of the main matters deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in the <hi>New Testament,</hi> that when they come to know Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <hi>ſavingly</hi> they do <hi>immediately</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thoſe <hi>Articles</hi> in <hi>another manner,</hi> and make a <hi>better uſe</hi> of them than they did <hi>before.</hi> And thus they will be excuſed from a great deal of <hi>Pains,</hi> they muſt otherwiſe take, to get the knowledge of theſe <hi>points,</hi> before they can apply themſelves, to make a <hi>far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Progreſs.</hi> Beſides, the <hi>notional knowledge</hi> of ſuch <hi>Articles</hi> if attended to, with any <hi>tolerable Application,</hi> will conduce very much to Peoples <hi>Conviction,</hi> and diſpoſe them to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> as the <hi>Christ</hi> and reſign up themſelves entirely to his <hi>Conduct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:41276:27"/>7thly, It is ſo far from being a <hi>Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> and <hi>Diſadvantage</hi> to the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> that Chriſt Jeſus hath taught ſo <hi>many Articles,</hi> it is its <hi>ineſtimable excellency.</hi> It is a <hi>ſingular Benefit,</hi> for which every good Chriſtian ought to be very <hi>thankful.</hi> Indeed if no Man could be a <hi>True Chriſtian,</hi> till he hath an <hi>explicite knowledge</hi> and belief of every thing Chriſt hath taught, then none but Men of <hi>extraordinary parts</hi> and <hi>pains</hi> could be <hi>True Chriſtians,</hi> if any could be ſo. But the matter is ſo ordered, that nothing is made neceſſary to <hi>conſtitute</hi> a Perſon a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> but what the meaneſt of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind</hi> is capable of; and yet there is no <hi>Indulgence</hi> to <hi>Sloth</hi> and <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> nor <hi>excuſe</hi> for <hi>wilful Ignorance</hi> in any, becauſe there is nothing neceſſary to make a Perſon a True Chriſtian, but his knowing that <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the Perſon <hi>God</hi> hath ſent, and <hi>commiſſioned</hi> to be the <hi>only Saviour</hi> of <hi>Sinners,</hi> ſo as to take Him <hi>unfeignedly</hi> to be his <hi>Lord.</hi> And this doth <hi>indiſpenſably</hi> oblige him to uſe his <hi>best endeavours</hi> to <hi>know,</hi> and make a <hi>right uſe</hi> of what Chriſt hath <hi>Revealed.</hi> And He hath
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41276:28"/> provided ſo <hi>abundantly</hi> for the impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and bettering of our <hi>Minds</hi> and <hi>Practices,</hi> that how long ſoever we live, we may be <hi>growing</hi> and <hi>increaſing</hi> in the knowledge of <hi>thoſe matters,</hi> which will exceedingly improve and beautifie our <hi>Intellectuals,</hi> advantage and adorn our <hi>Converſations</hi> and <hi>Lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let us remember what the Wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>Wiſdom is the principal thing, therefore get Wiſdom, and with all thy getting get <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> Prov. 4.7. Let us labour to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand aright the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and get the knowledge of <hi>Him</hi> as our <hi>Lord,</hi> and endeavour conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to grow up more and more in the knowledge of Him, and of what He hath revealed. Then we ſhall know by <hi>Experience,</hi> that the <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi> of this <hi>knowledge</hi> is ſuch, that all that words can expreſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, falls abundantly ſhort of diſcovering the <hi>whole Truth.</hi> The <hi>pleaſure</hi> that ariſeth from the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate <hi>diſcourſe</hi> concerning Chriſt Jeſus, is as much ſhort of what a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon perceives in <hi>himſelf,</hi> upon his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41276:28"/> knowing Chriſt Jeſus <hi>ſavingly,</hi> as the <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> which ſprings from the moſt <hi>Philoſophical</hi> deſcription of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> is ſhort of that pleaſure <hi>Jonathan</hi> felt in <hi>himſelf</hi> when his <hi>Eyes</hi> were <hi>opened,</hi> and all his <hi>faculties revived</hi> upon his <hi>taſting</hi> it. The <hi>excellency</hi> of <hi>Food</hi> is unexpreſſibly better perceived by an <hi>hungry Perſon,</hi> when he finds himſelf <hi>refreſhed</hi> and ſtrengthened upon his <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>digesting</hi> it, than by any words that can be uſed to ſet forth its <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Properties.</hi> When you come to know Chriſt Jeſus ſo, as to yield up your ſelves entirely to Him, you will be fully of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s mind, and <hi>account all things but loſs, for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jeſus your Lord.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:41276:29"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Awnſham</hi> and <hi>John Churchil.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>TAlent</hi>'s Chronological Tables, fol.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cambden</hi>'s <hi>Britannia,</hi> fol.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Boyl</hi>'s General Hiſtory of the Air, 4<hi rend="sup">0.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Machiavil</hi>'s Works.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Roger L'Strange</hi>'s <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s <hi>Fables,</hi> fol.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Baker</hi>'s Chronicle continued.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lock</hi> of <hi>Human <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> fol.</item>
               <item>— of <hi>Education.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— of <hi>Money, Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Trade.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tanner</hi>'s <hi>Notitia Monaſtica.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Wilkins</hi> of Prayer and Preaching, enlarged by Dr. <hi>Moor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich</hi> and Dr. <hi>Williams.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Hody</hi> of the Reſurrection.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>W. Temple</hi>'s <hi>Miſcellania</hi> compleat.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Patrick</hi>'s New Verſion of the <hi>Pſalms.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s <hi>Religion,</hi> twelves.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Le Clarc</hi>'s <hi>Logica,</hi> twelves.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Leighton</hi> Arch-Bp of <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> his <hi>Sermons:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Royal Grammar,</hi> &amp;c. octavo.</item>
               <item>Prince <hi>Arthur</hi> by Dr. <hi>Blackmore,</hi> fol.</item>
               <item>Three ſeveral Letters for Toleration.</item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Hopkins</hi>'s 4 Vol. of <hi>Sermons</hi> and other pieces.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Selden</hi>'s Table Talk, octavo.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe concerning the Love of God, twelves.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meriton</hi>'s <hi>Guide</hi> for <hi>Surveyors</hi> of <hi>High-ways,</hi> octavo.</item>
               <item>An Abridgement of Mr. <hi>Lock</hi>'s <hi>Eſay</hi> of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Wynn,</hi> octavo.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:41276:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
